DAN KLEIN: All right,
what are we doing?
We got estimates of the
values of each state.
So we've got a table.
Each one has a number, which is our
estimate of the score you will get
from that state going forward.
What we'd like to do is we'd like to
make them better by replacing each one
with an average of what you'd get in
the next time step plus the current
approximation in the future.
That's this Bellman update equation
that's written here.
What we'd like to do is we'd like to
take that average of our outcomes s
prime without knowing how
likely each s prime is.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to take samples of outcomes.
How can we get a sample for s prime?
How can we get a sample of what happens
if you take action pi of s
from state s?
There's only one way
to get that sample.
Wait until you find yourself in state s,
do pi of s, and carefully watch the
result and record it.
You have to do the action.
And every time you do the action, the
environment is nice enough to hand you
a sample back, which is one
of the possible outcomes.
So it looks like this in the equation
that we have and in the diagram that
I've been drawing.
You have one action that you
know you're going to take.
And you have many s primes
that can happen.
Of course, when you actually take
the action, only one of
those things happens.
Let's call it s1 prime.
If I'm in state s and I take this
action, pi of s, and s1 prime happens,
now I have an estimate of what my
score is going to be from s.
It's going to be the reward I just got,
this instantaneous reward here,
plus the discounted future
from the landing state.
Well what's the reward I just got?
I just got it, right?
So I know that number.
What's the discounted future value?
It's somewhere else in the table
that I'm maintaining.
And it's wrong.
But it's just been discounted
by gamma, so who cares.
Now of course, one sample is
not the same as an average.
I need more samples.
I need sample 2, I need sample 3, and
so on all the way up to sample n.
Now what would happen if I have
lots of samples from this
same state and action?
And for each of these samples I saw
various outcomes s prime, each one had
a reward, and a discounted
approximate future?
What would I do?
Well I'd say, really, the most informed
thing I can say about the
state s is that, on average, I'm going
to get the average of these samples.
So I could write down that, on average,
I get 1/n times the sum of
the end samples.
We're almost there.
If we could do this, we would be,
essentially, executing the policy
evaluation update.
We'd be taking that average according
to T, without knowing T. So it's
correct insofar as, with enough samples,
this implements that update.
There's something really wrong
with this algorithm.
What's really wrong with
this algorithm?
How did we get our first sample?
We got our first sample by finding
ourselves in state s and
taking the action pi.
You can't get your second sample,
until you're back in state s.
Well, how do you do that?
Well, you don't know.
You don't know what's going on.
This is reinforcement learning.
You don't even know what
your actions do.
How are you going to get
back to state s?
So you kind of can't do this.
Maybe someday you'll be in s again, but
you can't just keep executing the
same action from the same state.
Maybe, if you could rewind
time, you could do it.
You execute the action, rewind
back, and then try again.
But you can't do that, right?
If you had a crystal ball, maybe
you could do it going forward.
But you can't do that either.
So what do we need to do?
We need to somehow be satisfied
with the one sample we get.
Because once we get that sample,
we're off in some other state.
And who knows if we'll ever
be back to state s.
So that's the big idea in temporal
difference learning.
In temporal difference learning,
we learn from every experience.
Every time we undergo a transition
from some state s to some state s
prime, we're going to
update our values.
And it's gong to be a little tricky,
because we only get one sample of what
might have happened.
So we need to somehow make
sure that, over time, we
accumulate the right averages.
But right now, we've got one sample.
We've got to incorporate
it and move on.
The reason this is called temporal
difference learning is because we
compare our current estimate of a
value with what we actually see.
All right, so let's take a
look at how this works.
And then we'll see it in a demo.
We're doing temporal difference
learning right now of values.
So the policy is still
going to be fixed.
We're still evaluating this policy.
We're still not worrying about
how to choose actions.
That will come later.
The idea is we're going to move the
values towards whatever we actually
see happen.
It's going to be some kind of running
average, but we've got to be careful.
So here's the idea.
We imagine we were at state s.
Well, before we took any action, we had
some estimate of how good it was
that encapsulates all of
our knowledge to date.
So we've got some estimate V of s.
It's not correct, but it's
an approximation.
From s, we take an action.
In this case, we do what pi tells us.
And we land in some particular
sample outcome s prime.
So we get one of the many possible
outcomes of our actions.
We get the reward that's associated with
it, that's R. And then we get put
in a state s prime for which
we have an estimated future
utility from s prime.
So on one hand, we think we're
going to get V of s.
That's what our past experiences
has told us.
On the other hand, this particular time,
it looks like we're on track to
get this sample.
It looks like we're on track to
get the instantaneous reward
plus V pi of s prime.
So what do we do?
We've got our old experiences
all summarized in our value.
But then we have this new experience we
need to incorporate, which includes
a real reward, R, and then an
approximation that's been discounted
into the future.
So how do we take the average
of one thing?
What we do is we keep around our
old value with some weight.
And we average in the new
thing with some weight.
So we interpolate.
There's going to be some value, alpha,
called the learning rate.
Alpha is usually small.
You can imagine it's like
0.1 or something like
that, maybe even smaller.
And every time we get a sample of the
new value, which is a reward plus a
discounted future, we average it
in by interpolating it with
the old value estimate.
So we mostly keep around our old
information, but we roll in a tiny bit
of this new information.
And if we ever come back to here again,
we'll roll something else in.
And we'll end up with a kind
of running average.
So an important question here
is why we use alpha.
Why don't we keep track of every
experience we've ever had?
If we really, really wanted an even
average, that would be a way to
achieve it.
It turns out this is not only easier,
but it's in fact better.
We'll see why in a second.
Here's one way of writing the update.
It says, I have my current estimate.
I have my sample, which alone is noisy,
but which is good because it
represents an experience.
And I'm going to average them together
by interpolation where most of the
weight is on the old experience.
I can also write that by just algebraic
manipulation like this.
And this is another useful way of
thinking about this update.
It says, take your value and add to it
alpha times the difference between
what you thought would happen
and what actually did.
You can think of that as an error.
And this says, whenever you see an error
in your estimates, adjust your
estimate in the direction of the error
by some small step size alpha.
Why not step size 1?
Well, because then we wouldn't be
balancing all of our different
experiences.
So there's a trade-off.
Larger alphas learn faster.
Smaller alphas do a better job of
balancing across experiences.
OK, let's see a demo of that.
Here's a grid world.
In this grid world, we are
about to do temporal
difference learning of values.
Remember, that means we keep
a big table of values.
And guess what?
They all start off with zero, because
we have no idea what's going on in
this grid world.
The blue dot represents the agent.
And I'm going to issue commands.
And the agent will then
watch what happens.
So I'm going to try to go north.
I went north.
In this version, the living reward is
set to zero, so that we can see how
the exit rewards propagate.
In this case, no update happened,
because I thought that I was going to
receive a total utility of zero
from the start state.
I in fact received a zero.
And I landed in a state where I thought
there was zero left to come.
So I thought I was going
to get a zero.
I do seem to be on track to get zero.
Nothing to do.
So nothing interesting happens, until
I receive a non-zero reward, which I
receive not when I enter this square
here, but when I exit it.
Right now, I think I'm going to
get a zero total future score.
When I take the exit action, I will
in fact receive a plus 1.
And then I'll be forced to reconcile
the plus 1 I got with the zero I
thought I was going to get.
And right now, alpha is set to 0.5.
And so the average value
will now be 0.5.
And I update my array.
I play again.
So I go north.
Nothing happens.
All right, what happens when
I move into this square?
From here, I'm about to move east.
I think I'm going to get
a total score of zero.
Let's see what actually happens.
Well, I go east.
What did I receive that time step?
Zero.
But I landed in a state that looks,
right now, to be worth 0.5.
So on one hand, I thought
my total would be zero.
On the other hand, this experience says
I'm going to get zero plus 0.5.
I average them.
And I get the 0.25.
Now that's going to continue
happening.
As I exit here, that 0.5 approaches 1,
because I'm going to get 1 every time.
And as I go through here, now, when I
move into the next square, even though
I will receive no reward, I'll
land in a square which looks
like it's worth 0.25.
And I'll get half of that
as my value update.
And I'm going to execute this.
Notice that we learn about the square
we leave because, when I leave this
square, I'm going to learn the
my estimate of zero isn't
the best I can do.
I can do better.
I can say it's probably
more like 0.13.
All right, so you learn about
the state you leave, not the
state you land in.
And let me just do this a couple of
times, so you can see the values
propagating back.
All right.
Now what's the magic of this?
The magic of this is I am learning
the values of these squares.
And they're the values under the
policy that I'm executing.
What would happen if I went
the other way around?
Well, that start state looks worse
because, instead of landing in a nice
juicy 0.5, I just landed in zero.
On the other hand, when I get to here
and I go north, even though I've never
been in this state before and this is
my first experience with it, as soon
as I see that going north lands me at
0.98, I know that going north is
pretty good.
And so I'll have an update.
That's exactly the effect that direct
evaluation didn't have.
Now, of course, if I start doing dumb
things, I'll start getting values the
reflect this now dumb policy.
So we only get values that reflect
what's actually going on.
But it does average things
in the appropriate way.
And it does share information across
episodes in a good way.
OK, a couple of quick points.
First of all, we're taking an
exponential moving average here.
And that's because we're
doing this update.
We're doing an update that says the new
value is alpha times some Xn plus
1 minus alpha times the old value.
And you can think of this as
averaging things together.
But of course, new things
have more weight.
In the extreme case, when alpha is 1,
new things have all the weight.
If we actually worked out the algebra
and telescoped everything, we would
actually see that the form of this tells
you that most recent samples are
more important.
So the average here is an average, but
exponentially weighted where older
things are decayed.
And so we had a good question before,
which is, why would we not want to
take the extra effort to make sure
we were averaging things equally?
And the answer is, because the things
we're averaging have two components.
They've got the instantaneous reward,
which is absolutely correct.
And they've got an estimate
of the future.
The next time we come back to a state,
the estimate of the future state will
be better than it is now.
And so, more recent samples are
actually better, because they
incorporate better estimates
of the future.
And so there's this nice dove-tailing
of this update that's easy to do.
It also has a nice property of
remembering the past, but also slowly
forgetting it and down-weighting it
as our updates become better.
In essence, the Bellman updates have
been smeared across space and time.
We had a question about decreasing
the learning rate.
If you decrease it, then you
can actually converge
to the correct things.
But there's an art to decreasing it.
It can't go down too fast or too slow.
And we'll come back to
this point later.
OK, so we just saw a method of learning
the values of every state
under a policy that's executing, just
by watching the outcomes of every
transition.
This is great.
It's a model-free way of doing
policy evaluation.
We end up doing the Bellman updates, in
effect, taking those averages that
were hard to take without
the transition function.
And we do it without ever computing
a transition function.
We just let the sample frequencies
speak for themselves.
So that's great.
It did what we wanted.
But it's not going to work for
the general problem of active
reinforcement learning where we
want to not only evaluate,
but also choose actions.
Why is that?
Well, let's imagine we've
run this thing.
And we've got this big table
of state values.
For every state, I can tell you,
according to the policy we've been
running, it's worth seven points
in total and so on.
The problem is, if we want to turn
those values into a policy--
and in particular, we'll want to turn
them into a new policy which is,
hopefully, better than
the old policy--
now we're sunk.
And the reason why we're sunk is we
know how to produce a policy from
values, but it involves one
step of expect-a-max.
We would say the policy is whatever
action achieved the largest Q-value
for that state.
But of course, those Q-values involve
an average of their outcomes.
And we can't do that because, again,
we don't have T and R.
The key idea here is that, if we want
to be able to do action selection as
well, we should be learning not
just the values as we have
been, but the Q-values.
And in fact, this is why we even have
a notion of Q-values in this course.
They're critical for choosing actions
in reinforcement learning.
This idea of learning Q-values makes
action selection model-free as well,
because we just look at the Q-values
and choose whichever one's best.